Guide to the Tim Valentine Papers, 1982-1994 RL.01327
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tim Valentine papers
1982-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Valentine, I. T. (Itimous Thaddeus), 1926-
RL.01327
85.5 Linear Feet
40,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Tim Valentine, Congressman from the 2nd District of North Carolina, were acquired as a gift from Tim Valentine in 1994.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1926, Mar. 15 Born, son of I. T. and Hazel (Armstrong) Valentine, Nash County, N.C.
1948 A.B., Political Science, The Citadel, Charleston, S.C.
1952 LL.B. University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C.
1952-1982 Private practice, law, Nashville, N.C.
1955-1960 N.C. General Assembly, Raleigh, N.C.
1982-1994 Member of 98th-102nd Congresses from 2nd District, N.C.
Collection Overview
The Tim Valentine papers span the years 1982 to 1994. The collection consists of correspondence, press releases, speeches, legislation, committee files, and video and cassette tapes. Materials pertain to the political life and career of former Congressman Tim Valentine of North Carolina's second district.
Congressional committees Valentine served on and which are represented in this collection are: Agriculture Committee; Appropriations Committee; Armed Services; Banking, Finance, and Urban Affairs; Budget Committee; D.C. Committee; Education and Labor; Governmental Operations; House Administration; Interior and Insular Affairs; Energy and Commerce; Foreign Affairs; Judiciary; Merchant Marine and Fisheries; Post Office and Civil Service; Public Works and Transportation; Rules Committee; Standards of Conduct; Small Business; Veterans Committee; and the Ways and Means Committee. The Correspondence series covers constituents' opinions and concerns about issues that relate to these committees. Subjects include abortion, pesticides, labor, defense, education, taxes, prayer in public schools, and gun control. This series also includes personal correspondence from Valentine's friends and colleagues. The Legislative series allows one to track Valentine's stand on legislative issues through the voting records and legislative profiles. Other legislation files comprise health, welfare, education, transportation, and the Lake Gaston pipeline issue information. The Press series provides information on Valentine's campaign, his political and legislative beliefs, and events relevant to the time.
Valentine, I. T. (Itimous Thaddeus), 1926-
- Correspondence Files, 1983-1994
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials divided into three subseries: Personal, Washington Office, and District Office. Personal contains letters to colleagues, House members' requests for congressional bicentennial baseball cards, congratulations, and thank-yous to and from Valentine. Files arranged chronologically. (1-3, 1986-1994) Washington Office consists of Valentine's computer letter system of numbers corresponding to particular reply letters. (Box Nos. 4-34, 1985, 1990-1994) The District Office Correspondence uses a similar number system except numbers arrange letters by Valentine's committees (see box list). (35-52, 1983-1990) Both office's letters from constituents cover legislation and issues concerning abortion, wetlands' management, pesticides, labor, defense, education, monetary policy, taxes, prayer in public schools, and gun control. Both office files arranged by number system and then chronologically.
  - 1986-1987, 1989-1992, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - 1991-1992, 1994, Jan. - July, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1991-1992, 1994, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1985-1992Computer Letter Lists, 18 folders (Box 4)
  - 1993-1994Computer Letter Lists, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1990,0-799 Coded Constituent Letters, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1990,800-1999 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - 1990,2000-2799 Coded Constituent Letters, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1990-1991,2800-3999 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - 1991,4000-4999 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - 1990,1991,5000-6199 Coded Constituent Letters, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - 1991,6200-7399 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - 1991,7400-8399 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - 1991,8400-9199 Coded Constituent Letters, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - 1991-1992,9200-9999 Coded Constituent Letters, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - 1990, 1991-1992,10,000-10,799 Coded Constituent Letters, 9 folders (Box 15)
  - 1992,10,800-11799 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - 1992,11800-12799 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - 1990, 1992,12,800-13,799 Coded Constituent Letters, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - 1990, 1992-1993,13,800-14599 Coded Constituent Letters, 9 folders (Box 19)
  - 1990, 199314,600-15,099 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 20)
  - 1993,15,100-15,599 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - 1993,15,600-16,199 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 22)
  - 1990, 1993,16,200-16,699 Coded Constituent Letters, 9 folders (Box 23)
  - 1993, 16,700-17,299 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 24)
  - 1993,17,300-17,799 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 25)
  - 1993,17,800-18,399 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 26)
  - 1993,18,400-18,799 Coded Constituent Letters, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - 1990, 1993-1994,18,800-19,399 Coded Constituent Letters, 9 folders (Box 28)
  - 1994,19,400-19,999 Coded Constituent Letters, 6 folders (Box 29)
  - 1994,20,000-20,499 Coded Constituent Letters, 7 folders (Box 30)
  - 1994,20,500-21,099 Coded Constituent Letters, 5 folders (Box 31)
  - 1990,1994,21,100-21,599 Coded Constituent Letters, 14 folders (Box 32)
  - 1990,1994,21,600-31,006 Miscellaneous Correspondence 1987-1990, 49 folders (Box 33)
  - Miscellanious Correspondence; Retired Computer Letters, 1985-1992, 4 folders (Box 34)
  - 1986-1989,1-9,000, NRNs, 28 folders (Box 35)
  - 1983-1990,10,000 Agriculture Committee, 19 folders (Box 36)
  - 1983-1990,11,000 Appropriations Committee, 12,000 Armed Services Committee, 32 folders (Box 37)
  - 1983-1990,13,000 Banking Finance, and Urban Affairs Commitee, 14 folders (Box 38)
  - 1983-1990,14,000 Budget Committee; 15,000 D.C. Committee (Box 39)
  - 1983-1987,16,000 Education and Labor Committee, 18 folders (Box 39)
  - 1989-1990,16,000 Education and Labor Committee (Box 40)
  - 1983-1989,18,000 Governmental Operations Committee (Box 40)
  - 1983-1990,19,000 House Administration Committee, 16 folders (Box 40)
  - 1983-1990,20,000 Interior and Insurlar Affairs Committee (Box 41)
  - 1983-1987,21,000 Energy and Commerce Committee, 19 folders (Box 41)
  - 1989-1990,21,000 Energy and Commerce Committee (Box 42)
  - 1983-1986,22,000 Foreign Affairs Committee, 13 folders (Box 42)
  - 1987-1990,22,000 Foreign Affairs Committee (6 folders) (Box 43)
  - 1983-1987,23,000 J udiciary Committee, 17 folders (Box 44)
  - 1988-1990,23,000 Judiciary Committee, 4 folders (Box 45)
  - 1983-1990,24,000 Merchant Marine and Fisheries Committee; 25,000 Post Office and Civil Service Committee, 20 folders (Box 46)
  - 1983-1989,26,000 Public Works and Transportation Committee (Box 47)
  - 1986-1989,27,000 Rules Committee, 21 folders (Box 47)
  - 1986-1989,28,000 Standards of Conduct Committee and Small Business Committee; 29,000 Veterns Committee (Box 48)
  - 1983,198630,000 Ways and Means Committee, 11 folders (Box 48)
  - 1987,30,000 Ways and Means Committee, 4 folders (Box 49)
  - 1988-1989,30,000 Ways and Means Committee, 4 folders (Box 50)
  - 1989,30,000 Ways and Means Committee, 3 folders (Box 51)
  - 1986-1988,31,000 (Box 52)
  - 1983,1985Miscellaneous Correspondence, 13 folders (Box 52)
- Legislative Files 1983-1994
  Materials include voting records, legislative profiles,Congressional and constituent correspondence, information relating to Valentine's committees, and legislation. Subjects cover health issues, welfare, education, defense, taxes, transportation, and the Lake Gaston pipeline.
  Arrangement note
  Series currently not arranged.
  - 1983-1988, Voting Records, Legislative Profile (Box 53)
  - 1989-1994, Voting Records, Legislative Profile (Box 54)
  - 1983-1984, 1993-1994, Lake Gaston Pipeline (Box 55)
  - 1983-1994, Lake Gaston Pipeline, Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 56)
  - 1987-1990,Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 57)
  - 1983-1994,Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 58)
  - 1987-1992,Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 59)
  - 1985-1986, 1992-1994,Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 60)
  - 1988-1989, 1993-1994, Transportation Legislation, Defense, Taxes, Budget (Box 61)
- Press Files, 1982-1992
  Files contain speeches, press releases, floor statements, clippings, videotapes, and radio spot tapes. Topics consist of environmental, and budget issues. Video and radio spot tapes are primarily for Valentine's campaign.
  - 1982 (Box 62)
  - 1983 (Box 63)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 64)
  - 1983-1985 (Box 65)
  - 1985-1988 (Box 66)
  - 1989-1994 (Box 67)
  - 1984-1992 (Box 68)
  - Polls, Radio Spot Tapes (Box 69)
  - Surveys/Polls, VCR Cassettes, Radio Spot Tapes (Box 70)